<workproduct identifier="User Profiles" project="WebScarab"
stage="Requirements">
  <header>
    <date>$Date: 2002/10/30 20:47:11 $</date>

    <author>$Author: istr $</author>

    <owner>$Author: istr $</owner>

    <status value="Initial" />
  </header>

  <details>
    <H1>User Profiles</H1>

    <H2>"Scan Now Boy"</H2>

    <P>The "scan now boy" is a comic description for a sadly all
    to familiar breed of user that is not technically skilled but
    finds him / herself doing security assessments. These users
    typically only use automated tools, and don't really
    understand the process or technology behind them. They are
    only concerned with scanning and generating reports to
    impress others. They typically choose default settings or
    pre-selected settings. They relish shiny red buttons but like
    to know they could change everything if they understood what
    things did. GUI and reporting is important.</P>

    <H2>Security Consultant</H2>

    <P>The security consultant maybe a corporate employee or a
    professional services consultant. He is typically comfortable
    with automated and manual tools, has a basic understanding of
    some languages (often scripting languages like perl) and a
    reasonable understanding of web application technology like
    HTTP, HTML, SSL. He is looking to produce detailed
    assessments of applications and so is comfortable making
    configuration changes and validating results that do not
    appear to be correct. He / she understands the underlying
    technology used in automated tools. This user is looking for
    both an automated tool and one which is customizable and
    comprehensive enough to work in all potential work
    situations. Reporting is important.</P>

    <H2>WebAppSec Security Specialist</H2>

    <P>The webappsec security specialist is a user who has a deep
    knowledge and interest in web application and web services
    security. He / she can code in at least one OOP language and
    often several. He / she has a deep understanding of HTTP,
    SSL, HTML, XML, web architectures like MVCs and web
    technology like J2EE, .NET, CGI etc. He or she is capable of
    being (and maybe) a web developer but specializes in
    security. He / she can write their own exploits and tools if
    so desire or has time. This user wants to be able to get
    under the hood and customize and extend tools to their own
    liking and is looking for a comprehensive, accurate and
    extensible platform from which to perform services or check
    applications they have developed. Accuracy and depth of
    checks is important.</P>
  </details>

  <issues>
    <item>Ask professor for permission.</item>
  </issues>

  <metrics>
    <item>If it measures the audience properly.</item>
  </metrics>

  <traceability>
    <impacts stage="Implementation"
    identifier="User_Support_Materials" />
  </traceability>

  <history>
	 $Log: User_Profiles.xml,v $
	 Revision 1.1  2002/10/30 20:47:11  istr
	 Initial revision
	
	 Revision 1.3  2002/05/24 08:06:02  zedshaw
	 Fixed problems with the XML.
	
   2002/05/24 07:44:04  zedshaw Added Mark's user analysis documents.
   2002/05/17 19:50:50 donalphonso moved workbook 
	 2002/05/05 17:21:16 zedshaw Initial import of project workbook
	</history>
</workproduct>


