
<workproduct identifier="Intended Development Process" project="WebScarab" stage="Project Management">
  <header>
		<date>$Date: 2002/10/30 20:47:10 $</date>
		<author>$Author: istr $</author>
		<owner>$Author: istr $</owner>
		<status value="Initial" />
	</header>
	
  <details>
  <p>The development process for the WebScarab project will be a simple, typical open source
	process where individuals work on different components of interest as needed towards a 
	common goal.  Since this model is characterized by disconnected, sometimes chaotic,
	activity, there will need to be a set of processes in place to help everyone communicate
	the progress of the project and its direction.  To facilitate this, there are certain
	things we can do:</p>
	
	<ul>
	<li>Use a set of workproducts that quickly document the design of the project and other 
	administrivia.  This is important both as a record of events, but also as a means of
	communicating what needs to be done and what has been done.</li>
	<li>Use a set of clear testing methodologies (such as Unit tests) that everyone can run
	from their own computers and use to verify code.</li>
	<li>Have a mailing list (with archives) for the project which allows us to share ideas and 
	stay on top of status.</li>
	<li>Utilize task lists to determine the path of development.</li>
	</ul>
	
	<p>Since many people are very anxious to write code, and not so enthusiastic to write
	workproducts, we need to develop a technique to make them not such a chore.  I believe
	the best methodology is the following (to be revised as needed):</p>
	
	<ul>
	<li>Start with anything you like:  Unit Tests, Working Code, Workproduct/Docs, or even 
	raw design ideas.  It should be something that is needed by the project, but not
	necessarily.</li>
	<li>Get your initial stab at the design to a point that it is sharable and announce it on 
	the list.  Have others look at it and comment.</li>
	<li>Incorporate improvements into the design, and write another piece of the puzzle:  Unit
	Tests, Working Code, or Workproducts.</li>
	<li>Throw away anything that is not working.</li>
	<li>Continue to iterate over each of the three work items (Unit Tests,
	Working Code, Workproducts), releasing them for review.</li>
	<li>When they are complete enough, begin to integrate them into the project.  Depending on
	the type of component, this may need to be done during development.</li>
	<li>If all integration works, and everyone else's Unit Tests are working properly, then you
	can release it in alpha stage.  This allows others to verify their work against yours.</li>
	<li>After alpha stage for your component, then it should be in the project and will be
	maintained as usual.  Remember to continually revisit your component (or those of others)
	as changes are made and your Unit Tests break.</li>
	</ul>
	
	<p>Notice that these steps are in a kind or order, but don't necessarily have to be done in
	that order.  People work differently, so whatver works for you is fine.  The only requirement
	is that three things are produced for each thing you work on:  Working Code, Unit Tests,
	Workproducts/Documentation.  With these three things, it is very easy for everyone to stay
	in communication with eachother.</p>
	
	
  </details>

  <issues>
    <item>Verify that this process works for everyone and refine it</item>
  </issues>

  <metrics>
    <item>Number of developers producing each output</item>
  </metrics>

  <traceability>
    <impacted-by stage="Design"
    identifier="System Architecure" />

    <impacts stage="Design" identifier="System Architecture" />
  </traceability>

	<history>
	$Log: Intended_Development_Process.xml,v $
	Revision 1.1  2002/10/30 20:47:10  istr
	Initial revision
	
	Revision 1.1  2002/05/17 19:49:16  donalphonso
	moved workbook
	
	Revision 1.2  2002/05/13 06:25:37  zedshaw
	Initial dev process created.  Very rough.
	
	Revision 1.1  2002/05/05 17:21:16  zedshaw
	Initial import of project workbook
	
	</history>
</workproduct>


